this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this is Nate black for software
engineering radio I'm joined today by
Peter Zaitsev Peter is the CEO of pre
Kona the company with deep expertise in
open-source databases Peter was an early
employee at my sequel a B eventually
leading the company's high-performance
group he co-founded percona and assumed
the role of CEO in 2006 peter is
co-author of high-performance my sequel
optimization backups and replication
Peter welcome to software engineering
radio thank you
Peter there are so many databases out
there and more being created all the
time so in this episode we wanted to
cover first how many databases do you
need in a new application and second how
to go about choosing so could you please
tell us why choosing an open-source
database is a difficult problem yeah
well first I would say it's not about
the open source database it is about
open source databases right if there may
be more than one for for your
application I think we had this kind of
an interest in pivot recently where we
had the scene and if a lot of
consolidation where you would get the
unit you know decade ago for example if
you would look into some very small
number of a legion a Legion database
right you would look at either Oracle or
MySQL when it comes to the open source
database right and now the trend has
been changing there we have a lot of
database which are really purpose-built
right and so you may well need more than
one database to choose to
in your vacation yeah we had a few
episodes that referenced this
development one was Michael Stonebraker
talking about volt DB and he referenced
the paper he wrote in 2006 called the
area of what the era of one-size
databases is over or at the era of
one-size-fits-all databases is is over
yes that's right and since then we've
also covered multi model databases and
polyglot persistence is what your is
what you're talking about related to
those topics oh yes yeah I think if
you're multiple trends which are Davichi
going on right now right so and let me
maybe talk a little bit about that so
from one standpoint one of a general
software engineering trend right at
least one of the patterns we see is
marker services and what is interesting
about about micro services is that makes
services often in many case on the data
and provide the external API on access
to that right and different micro
services may chose the different
database technologies which are best
suited for their needs
right so for example your mic reserved
micro service responsible for search may
use elastic while your micro service
which is responsible for your order
tracking and delivery right may use some
traditional the relational database such
as MySQL right
that is one trend another interesting
trend is of course the raise of a cloud
very in the past it was really hard to
scale the number of databases because
you would need so much experience in
house to operate and manage rows now
with threads of the clouds and database
as a service pattern then it makes it
very easy for developers to spin up in
the cloud their database instances right
they want and there is very little
friction for you using both MySQL
MongoDB elastic and radius all in the
same application
is this just due to it being easier to
provision the hardware or in this case
virtual hardware or there are other
trends that are causing the cost of
operations to go down no no it's not
just about their hardware and I think
the hardware itself is is really minimal
here right then we saw a shift from
let's say your kind of conventional data
center to the cloud right and you you
have a services as Amazon ec2 and EBS
came out right it was relatively easy to
automate deployment of your your
hardware and services at those days
right but the databases are particularly
kind of technologies right they are very
important for your applications if they
die badly they lose all your data right
and if you don't have your data well
chances I don't have your business right
so they're not you cannot have like such
relaxed approach try to make it to
manage in the database as you may with
your with your web service right which
you know if you if it dies probably
nothing happens right there Web Services
the web service can take over right so
real change here happened when the
database-as-a-service technology such as
the Amazon address or aura right or even
more proprietary technologies as
dynamodb became available right because
those technologies they kind of manage
themselves in a sense of if you get this
kind of service its provision that
provides you high variability right it
takes care of your backups at least in
some way and so on and so forth right so
as a engineer as developer you don't
really need to take care of all that
messy operations you would still need to
do if you adjustable your database on
ec2 environments right on your own
this question was originally I I was
thinking about the risk of lock-in to a
particular database technology but that
seems to potentially extend to these
databases of service
situations is lock-in a big risk oh yeah
yeah no of course it is
of course it is it is a big big risk
with with locking right and this is why
from my standpoint if you are choosing
the bay ever databases everything being
equal you are better off to choose the
open source database right or a set of
open source database of course cloud
cloud vendors make it very seductive to
get on their database as a service
offering because they problem is so much
and so much simplicity ease of use and
so on and so forth which does of course
come with huge vendor lock-in because a
lot of our services are this side
designed to be like as a famous Hotel
California right where it's very easy to
check in but it's very hard to check out
all of them of course from his
comparability with open source database
systems but this is one way
comparability Amazon makes it very easy
for you to move to from from MySQL to
Amazon Aurora with my school
comparability but they also make it much
harder to move out right wherever is due
to the scalability right wherever some
other additional features which they
hope you would rely on right so so yes I
would say that then the login is a
concern I'd like to come back to that
later when we talk about different
open-source licenses I think this is in
a way related but first I want to cover
the rest of the roadmap or I guess these
are more high-level questions
what's the situation where the choice of
the database is really important and we
need to care about it a lot versus
situations where it's it doesn't matter
well I think there are multiple angles
to that right and if you look at where
our choices for databases is more
important of course we are speaking
about the applications each or more
implicit which are a more
mission-critical which a large scale so
for example the efficiency the in this
case becomes very very important but I
think it's also important just in a
different way when you are starting to
to build your application and it's kind
of small and easy it just goes through
the different thought process right so
for example if you are developer and you
are just trying to build some small
application what database you to choose
well chances are that is a database you
already know and that is a database you
can you know build that verification
live right which would be very different
from the choice some fortune 500
enterprise is doing or making commitment
right for the next decade right or allow
it for a whole enterprise okay so it
comes down to expertise and what you
know I think that you're echoing what
was what was said in the polyglot
persistence episode which is essentially
go first with your expertise or what
you're comfortable with and then have
some kind of migration path forward well
I would say this is right right you want
to to choose what you are comfortable
with right hopefully as an engineer you
have experience so you understand where
you are trying to fit there I was go
like a square peg in the round hole
right because nothing Goods a good
discount is going to come out from that
right less less much less experience
engineering they have a sometimes they
don't have that and they may have huge
surprises then we run into some problems
your database for example using MySQL as
a database and you start with an
application when you need to have some
reporting functionality in them BOM
surprise MySQL doesn't really run the
analytical queries very fast somebody
who has experienced deep experience
right even medium level experience of
MySQL would know that somebody who
doesn't that they want and they may
actually I think it would be great if I
would know about that one so I would
have designed my system different great
that leads to the next section where I
wanted to talk about the application
data and storage model of your
application so when we did the show on
multi model databases we talked about
finding the data model that fits your
usage pattern and that episode actually
talked a lot in detail about different
data models and their suitability for
various features could you talk a little
bit about that to give listeners an idea
about some specific open source
databases and how they map to data
models or use cases that fit really well
with the fee the way that that data
model or storage model operates yes sure
sure I think then you look about a data
model there are kind of two different
layers here right you may be may want to
think about one is what your logical
model right that is how you developer
upgrades
right the data the average is more of a
physical model that's how a database
engine stores that and that or can be
important because what is going to be
able to do fast and what's not will
depend on that so if you look at their
at at the logical model some of the most
popular models right now would be either
your relational database model right
such when you have SQL databases
faithful that model and the great thing
about this model it is very expressive
like literally all kind of applications
has been built on on that model right
but at the same time that requires a lot
of thought in design in advance the
other model which has been raised in
more
more recently is there document in which
case you do not have to do such an
extensive database design as a
relational model often your queries can
be more complicated and easy to
understand it's also often kind of more
I would say more similar to how you
present the data in the modern
applications right so for example if you
if you are front-end developers your
chances are using javascript and and
have been working if a JSON data a lot
writes the J data structure as a JSON
objects guess what you can get those
objects pushed directly in the document
store database not so much into into a
relational database and you can have a
queries convenient queries on them
right in a document storage base the
third one which i think is very popular
because there is also a very simple key
value or databases right that is also
very simple to understand and they have
been used for years for things like you
know caching and similar simple
applications now this is of course not
an extensive list right you have also
there the graph databases right and
other data structures right for example
very popular database called radius it
offers you something like you know maybe
10 or more different data structures
which you can use for different
different data models so that is what I
would say from with front-end or your
logical data structure now if you look
at their more physical concepts right
then in this case you have I think
couple of interesting dimension we
should happen in so far one is your
database we should primarily designed
for a data store on disk right another
there are also in memory databases right
an in-memory database can often do some
special optimization on the data access
patterns when you can serve a date
really really fast but then obviously
amount of data you can store in memory
is limited right now the other
difference you would see for relational
databases you also have things like
rogue store versus colum store right and
is typically seen as wherever's database
engine is designed for your analytical
applications right runyan some you know
complicated queries which crunch through
millions billions right even trillions
of rows versus your more online
transactional applications which
typically run simple queries which you
know scan or modified maybe hundreds you
know thousands of rows right they have a
different you know physical storage
structures right which is designed for
so different use cases in order to get
started in choosing a database or
databases then I would have to have some
kind of idea about the what you call the
logical model and what kind of logical
model was appropriate for my application
and then I would have to know what
what's the set of open-source databases
that that's in that space so can you
walk through a little bit the decision
process or how how could I inform myself
better about that decision well one
thing I would I would suggest first
write is yeah especially it comes to
open source it is better to travel the
road well-traveled traveled right or use
the popular open source database
technologies right because that is River
is a lot of experiences you will find
books you'll find forums you'll find
local user groups support right and if
you stuck it is very easy to to get help
alright some Brian my standpoint you can
go ahead and look at a number of lists
of a top open source database
technologies right you can use you know
DB engines for example is a very popular
kind of this benchmark of a polarity of
different open source data not just open
source all databases you can also look
at something like stack overflow
developer survey they also talk well
about what databases are popular among
different
on developers right which i think is a
great way to understand where the
traction is and where the world is he's
going right and in my opinion you want
to stick to the top ten
database technologies unless you really
really need something something
different you have a very strong reason
to go with that in you and the exotic
database technology which will just give
you that 10x advantage right so that is
I think your most important choice out
there now and if you set that as a
baseline then there are not as many kind
of freely choices out there right
because if you think about you know
let's say document store well there is a
MongoDB which is by far the largest very
he is also a Couchbase coming up or you
can also use doc store functionality
provided by my squirrel doc store write
or use JSON store in in Postgres right
which is little bit less convenient but
you can still use it right relational
databases you have my squirrel and
Postgres fees are you know by far the
most popular kind of traditional
transactional open source open source
database right so yeah I think that's
how it goes
does Cassandra also fit into that list
yes that's right yeah Cassandra is
obviously also in at least right but I
think Cassandra is interesting right
because when people think about
Cassandra they I don't think you think
about that as a technology she has the
easiest to use the developer interface
but it it's really at the same time very
well designed for the large-scale
multiple data center application right
if you want to build an application
where the whole world is your playground
then Cassandra is one of technologies
you should surely look at perhaps I
could say you know I as an ambitious
developer I want the world to be my
playground so why shouldn't I then just
always choose Cassandra well you know
what because there isn't
free lunch right that is I think is a
very interesting observation from from
my side right I mean if you look at any
technology company out there right
obviously they promote via technology
right and they want to explain as you
know why it's make sense and points and
focus the discussion point to things
where it has advantages right but at the
same time you know when you make a
decisions it's always come with benefits
and drawbacks right in this case there
is no absolute silver bullet engineer
and then the samsu solution just has it
all right I mean and I think that is if
at least for me that is the first
question I ask right if somebody comes
to me and sell me their wonderful
technology right and go for all the
benefits and say ok well tell me when
you suck because that is what I'm
interested and if you say they are
perfect absolutely for everything then
there is that's obviously not reality
right I will know what they're trying to
mislead me so yes when I speak about
Cassandra right now as I mentioned that
is the technology which you can run
across multiple data centers right but
and really be very successful with
writing and multiple data center data
being automatically reconciled for you
and so on so forth but that means you
have to work with a much more
complicated data environment with
eventual consistency right it's much
easier for developers to say hey you
know what my data is simply consistent I
read the data the millisecond traitor I
so I write the data so right and then
millisecond later I read the data and
they have that correct value out there
it's much more complicated to reconcile
saying well you know I have a
modification out there but it may not
make it to some other you know data
center location over time right and then
it also goes into the flexibility of
schema and and so on and so forth now I
think to what you want to make the sense
right is my advice to developers who
would be too
do not have that gig on tamanna' right
if you right I mean I see so many people
listening to those let's say talks about
how Facebook built their environment and
saying oh that is exactly what to do and
I won't say no no that exactly what you
shouldn't do because you know it took
them many years and a billions of
dollars of investment to get to that to
that infrastructure right if you want to
start then when you want to probably to
start looking what you know Facebook has
been doing then they started but just
map it at the you know new technology
landscape and this is focus on
simplicity and productivity first and
foremost it sounds like there's a
spectrum of flexibility in the
technology in a sense you talked about
document stores and how they give you
flexibility in terms of the schema
definition and then maybe relational
databases would be I think somewhere in
the middle because they don't
necessarily require you to know your
access pattern in advance you can do
things like define secondary indexes
later whereas I think a technology like
Cassandra requires you to know in a
sense your access pattern and design
your keys that you're going to use to
access that data in advance before you
start putting data into the database so
that would put it even further to the
side of the spectrum where you need to
plan that's right now that are out you
need to plan a lot more with with
Cassandra said documents database such
as MongoDB they also support secondary
indexes right but they do have a
relatively limited support for the power
of things like a joins and sub queries
what you can do very easily right with
SQL right and then we spoke about this
productivity right I think what is very
important to know here is what the
productivity is also very much in our
beholder right because find a lot of
developers which know SQL pretty well
right and they say hey you know what I
can get so productive with SQL fast at
the same time if you have the average
which has been you know bred on you know
JavaScript right and they haven't a note
familiar of SQL in the relational data
model for them it is weird it's now you
know inconvenient and it's hard for them
to be productive at faster is relational
underrated in the current environment it
seems to be getting a bad rap you know
this is kind of very interesting right I
believe in you every new generation
right in and I think in our development
engineer environment generations are
yeah you know for every think about like
five years right no twenty years old
right they want to do something you
right then you want to invest something
new and exciting right and the
relational databases they have that wrap
of something something old but even more
I think a problem with relational
database what they had that reputation
of being being not scalable right
because if you look at that at the first
generation of scalable systems right
would be as Cassandra or as MongoDB
there you have to give up a lot of your
relational database properties right
including like you know acid consistency
you know and so on so to achieve that
kind of skill ability to you know
hundreds many thousands of nodes right
and for the new generation and you say
hey you know what we do not want to
change technology or think technology if
we really have to scale to hundreds of
database nodes those technologies right
they react attractive to them right now
this is changing and you may have heard
the term called new SQL right that is
have a databases which are as feature
full as your conventional relational
database right but which are as scalable
as database as MongoDB or Cassandra
right that is what that name typically
implies very and I think that is what is
going on more recently on the market
right and I think that's why really
databases actual from getting the second
look okay but does that apply to
Postgres and MySQL or maybe things in
the top 10 or is this something that
still kind of on horizon
no well uh kind of yes and no right so
if you look at bare-bones MySQL or
Postgres
single node database systems right
they're designed to run a database on
the single server you can often scale
you reads by using replication right you
can also deploy manual Chardon like
pretty much every large-scale MySQL user
a space book mmm all right has done
right but the it's kind of it's painful
right at the same time we have their
technology speech protocol compatible
coming up right so for example you may
have heard about cockroach TB which is
MySQL sort of PostgreSQL protocol
compatible database which is scalable
across larger number of nodes there is
also tidy B database which is MySQL
protocol compatible right and also open
source but which is also scale scalable
also in both net acknowledges there are
some add-ons right you can think about
them as a higher level maybe some sort
of proxy which makes them highly
scalable so example for Postgres verbose
technology called like situs from
Saito's data which would allow you to to
scale PostgreSQL conveniently and that
actually was acquired by Microsoft just
a couple of weeks ago right as I think a
validation of that technology success
interaction for my square they have
technology called Vitas which is
something which was born in YouTube in
Google and now deployed also by you know
number of successful companies latches
such as slack and I think oh I forget
strife or square or wonderful barnacles
to write which also really give you
their properties of no sequel database
while having your foundational storage
level as MySQL opposers digitalocean is
the easiest cloud platform to deploy
manage and scale applications of any
size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software the customers
love digitalocean stands out from the
crowd due to its simplicity high
performance and no billing surprises
join a community of over 3.5 million
developers on digital ocean sign up with
a free $100 infrastructure credit at do
dot CEO / se radio it sounds like these
technologies these add-on technologies
as you described them have something to
do with operations but then you've also
talked about different storage engines
which are compatible with for instance
my sequel I might be able to replace the
default storage engine with something
that's based on log structured merge
tree as you mentioned so is are these
two different things are they the same
thing can you please explain that yeah I
mean these are different things you're
talking about so what I talked about the
Chardon one of the great things or great
challenges for scaling your single
server database to a multiple server is
something which is called Chardon right
and which is really bane of development
a developer's existence because what
that means now instead of just you know
connecting to a single database and
running your query which can join as
many tables as as you like and so on so
if you have to somehow manually go to
multiple databases stage the data adjust
or on them and then somehow integrate
that in your application right that is
what the manual chardon is at worst
right and if you look at the
technologies what I mentioned such as
Vitas they can say hey you don't have to
do that we provide this top layer which
does that all for you you just run your
as its conventional and we spread it
across multiple nodes the tribal
resultset merge em do whatever for you
as well as handle what you mentioned as
a operational pains right which also
does exist in the in those life's life
scale environments right now the second
question what you mentioned about the
cave is storage engine right especially
in a MySQL case we do or have multiple
storage engines which have a different
properties and which are responsible how
your data is being stored and processed
right the most popular MySQL storage
engine is called energy B and that is a
you know pretty conventional storage
engine in fact somebody who implemented
that years ago really looked at what
Oracle dasu right and pretty much
implemented a lot of similar ideas in
the open source open source environment
now the other storage engine which is
available for MySQL is called my rocks
it's based on rocks DB which is
technology which was created in in
facebook there they wanted the storage
engine which is a more efficient for our
workloads right and that is something
that you can use with MySQL right and
get the better performance right or in
many cases reduce the costs by choosing
that bad storage engine as you mentioned
it is based on log structured merge
trees instead of B trees which energy B
is based on and log structured merge
trees they handle rights especially
inserts much more much more efficiently
than then in energy B and have a b-tree
bay storage engines okay so it's sounds
like a combination of factors that go
into well there are a few different
parameters it seems like there that are
moving one is you said these add-on
technologies that
make both operations but also
development easier because I don't have
to think about a lot of the under
underlying issues of manual sharding
targeting a specific node but then also
there are use other decisions so it I'm
not sure we're getting closer to a
understanding of how to choose the
database I'm I'm almost getting more
confused okay yeah yeah yeah well that
is it that's right that's right well
look I mean I think you go deeper and
deeper right and this is like you know
feeling an onion as a strike would say
right I mean a you see just more layers
and layers out there now now the good
thing in this case right what a lot of
those problems they really happen at at
large scale right and that is I think
what is very important to understand is
what the questions you need to answer
the on the small scale and a large scale
right very entirely it's very different
right so for example if you are not
operating on the Facebook scale you can
use standard built-in energy be storage
engine and you will be just absolutely
fine that's probably it is even better
choice for you because as I mentioned
you want to stay with the crowds right
and energy B is by far the more popular
storage engine than when my rocks right
in this case so so yes I mean if you go
go back and say well I am developer
right I'm trying maybe starting my new
startup maybe I'm trying to build
application right in my current company
and I want to see look at the databases
what what you want to choose right the
in this case I would start a question if
you have your own any preference right
if you are familiar with that database
and have a preference that is a very
good shortcut and in this case I would
evaluate wherever your database of
choice is is reasonable for application
you are trying to trying to build right
because for example if you are
you know building the application for
you know banking or e-commerce right and
your database technology doesn't say you
which you're comfortable with doesn't
support asset transactions well maybe
you need to go ahead and you know learn
the new technology right that would be
my first initial initial step right and
and as the time goes right what often
happens in this case if you look at us
technology they've developed in many
cases you start off single technology
but then you shop certain P things away
and introduce some more technologies to
the mix as you if a certain features of
your complexity became more complicated
or if if it just became much more you
know you need much more scale ok this
gets to the topic of polyglot
persistence so we would at a certain
level of scale will take the hit of
adding some additional complexity by
adding a new database technology to the
system how do you approach that how do
you approach that problem do you what do
you recommend for people to do how do
you know when it's time to add a new
technology versus try some more advanced
techniques to get your existing
technology to scale well I think that is
a very that is a very good question
right so I think it fell off the
question I would ask right the and often
that is sort of like a management is to
ask that question is OK what is the
reason that new technology is being
introduced because in many cases what I
see the reason is hey I want to play hey
cute toys cool toys right or hey I want
to get this technology it will look good
at my resume right arriv and actual you
know great technical reasons to to do
that and look and that may be ok right
maybe as it shows you can say well you
know what I want to retain that top
talent I have and I have to give them
toys to play sometime right but then you
also have to
understand the risks of such a decision
and let me tell you a story about this
topic so I remember a few years ago I
was visiting a customer and we were
talking about some log storage and
little well you know what we store logs
in MySQL but everybody knows MySQL is a
bad technology for storing logs where is
this Cassandra technology which you know
is based on LS m trees which are right
optimized right okay well I would ask
him okay
how much log files do you store I would
think maybe that's a terabyte so more
he'll say well you know I'm at about
10,000 lines a day well I would tell him
what at this point 10,000 times a day it
doesn't really matter right you can
store it in my squirrel you can store
them you know in in Cassandra right you
can even store em in the flat files and
graph them it will still from
performance standpoint who would not
really matter so then you know as it
happens if consultant in right you just
give you advice and leave and I visit
them again maybe kind of six months
later and you look at some performance
problem and that was asking okay can I
take a look at your logs and they would
look at me and say well you actually
have a problem restore logs in Cassandra
and that guy who managed read Cassandra
he recently left and we don't have
anybody else of Cassandra experience so
we don't really know how to get them out
right so this case is of course maybe
kind of trivial but that gives a good
idea is as you introduce more
technologies to a mix you have to make
sure you have either somebody in the
team or a vendor relationship so you can
montale them on the scale that you need
to do right which does introduce more
complexity you know more cost in your
environment as well that's great it gets
into questions that are I think less
obvious things to consider yeah let me
actually say something else about this
case so I want to also say at the same
time you should not do things which are
you know stupid or ugly right
I remember at at some time we would do
such a you know crazy stuff with my
school to try to make it full text
search work right for example which
doesn't scale well at all right it is
much better choice in this case is a hey
you know what this technology just
doesn't fit let us go ahead and use
elastic right and in many cases the
challenge in this case can be what your
current vendor or your team may be
resistance to introduce in some of those
additional technologic knowledge right
in this case for you know all kind of
kind of reasons right and this i think
is very important for managers right to
look and say well you know what that
doesn't smell right that is it really
looks like we're using the hammer to get
their screws into a wall right and while
we may make it happen if you hit really
really hard right that doesn't look
right right and then in the that is a
very good reason to consider a verdict
notice to use are there situations where
you want to also simplify the system and
reduce technology because clearly
there's a cost as you mentioned to
having expertise and then also
operational cost yes of course in that
you don't want to use too many too many
technologies right the in this case much
more than your application requires and
and in some cases you may want want to
reduce your number and here i think
couple of interesting trends which going
on right like i think they're multimodal
databases that is I think one affair
important play to say hey you know what
instead of having that complexity or for
all virus technologies just use one
technology which does it yeah does it
all for you it's it's yet to see right
from my distant point how many people
who already adopted a variety of
technologies which move to this approach
but I think that is a very appealing for
people who know we have variable data
model needs right and they would want to
standardize on one technology instead of
instead of many but there is not very
interesting trend going on which is
about technologists learning from each
other and kind of copying each have a
fee for each share features in some
extent so let me give you example in
MySQL there is a docstore interface now
available which allows you to pretty
much have MongoDB like experience in
chunks of storing your data in terms of
in terms of the driving it right from a
server at the same time if you look at
MongoDB for years they have introduced
something similar to be join right to be
able to have at least some basic support
right for SQL libraries in terms of
Cassandra we have a language which is
called cql right which is not the same
buts and that's similar to a sickly SQL
language right which is the core of your
productivity of relational databases
right so that is also a trend which is
happening well and of course Postgres
right Postgres they also have a lot of
features added over last year's in terms
of adjacent store
right store in the JSON documents
processed in the drive in them
effectively okay what does this tell us
in terms of how to make our decision
does it mean that like the choice
doesn't matter as much because we can go
in a sense from you know since the
features are blending together as my
sequel adopt some MongoDB like features
or or what is it what does it tell you
well from from my standpoint I think
that if we choice still matters right
because while there is certain
exchangeable features right or you know
cross-pollination right I think is a
good word to use here happens it is
still far from complete right for
example I mentioned CQL
right the casandra's language it's it's
good enough
some basic SQL like fishes but that's
nowhere as powerful as a full-blow and
SQL implementation or this way we talk
about the my school being a dog store
yes it
it has allows you to use MySQL and some
simple applications but it has not as a
broad support in the drivers and the
frameworks right it also doesn't have
the same scalability MongoDB among the
offers right what I say in this case is
what there is work going on in the open
source ecosystem and Beyond is to
simplify choices right like you
mentioned the paper of Michael
Stonebraker
right in terms of one database it's all
error is over and indeed over the last
decade we had a huge number of open
source databases I know just open source
special purpose database in general
created but this kind of has a pendulum
it goes back and forth right now they
are looking at that and say wow there
ask so much variety or is so much
choices wouldn't be fantastic if my
database could do a lot of it if not all
so I don't have to run so many
technologies right and there is a lot of
movement in that direction software
engineering radio episode 199 Michael
Stonebraker
he breaks it into three parts OLTP which
is kind of what relational database
technology targets data warehousing
which I think people can think of as
when you have lots and lots of data and
you want to run analytics on the data
and then he puts these no sequel
technologies and pretty much everything
else into like a third category and his
prediction was that eventually a lot of
the no sequel people will be moving more
towards having sequel like features
whether that's high level language for
accessing the data whether that's
retrofitting some type of transaction
capability and essentially that the
people developers wanted those features
is that something that that you've seen
I agree in terms of you know
cross-pollination reaches which is
happening
right and in many cases I would say
they're from no sequel engines v.i.c in
what the SQL like features are being
added but they are not not being
replaced and a lot of that has to deal
with the engagement of developers right
now if you would take a look at that
developer writing the code for example
in in in JavaScript right or Python and
if you would see them accessing
MongoDB versus MySQL or Postgres is
MongoDB looks so natural right in this
case you really pretty much see that as
an extension of your language you access
it almost like it would access your own
local data structure right compared with
with SQL you actually have to write you
know SQL query right if you are not
relying on your M framework which is
going to do that that for you right and
I don't think they're going to just give
it up right because that is so far from
so convenient for simple applications
but at the same time for complicated
data retrieval needs the SQL and SQL
derivatives prove itself to be a very
powerful language okay so it gets back
to where you are in the development
lifecycle and what your needs are in
terms of scalability that's right now
and let me say something else right if
you look at this kind of big choice
which often happens docstore right or
document model versus a relational model
I think a couple of things which are
important here in many cases when you
look at the document store it's also
often called schema less right and that
is often what developers love because
that means I don't have to think in
advance what columns I'm going to have
right or even more complicated structure
what kind of you know joins I have to
write right I can just evolve my schema
as I like I'm writing a code I can say
oh I want to store a size here
boom audit where attributes to my data
structure and here it goes into a
database right now and that is very good
for productivity of today right at the
same time in relativity is always schema
right
it just it may not be in a database it
may be in your application and as the
time goes many developers find what
maintaining the schema in your
application is actually pretty painful
right if over here you have you know the
created 40 different variants of that
schema and you have all the different
objects so if all those data structures
store in a database
it is very hard and painful to reliably
protest over that in your application
right and that is when people say well
you know what that is good they had a
really restriction of that relational
database which kept us more disciplined
right so what is happening here from one
standpoint is the noise QL databases way
target that problem of course in recent
Monkey version so you would have a
variability to validate your documents
has been added exactly to reduce that
you know free-for-all approach right in
this case but then from an other side
you also may may see some of the
questions okay how do I the question
what there may be there is value in more
thought-out schema design with
relational database enforces very you
may lose although it's kind of a
first-day productivity some bad but when
you reduce your pain over a long period
of time what exactly is the trade-off
then and is it simply that when I'm
using a relational database with the
schema of thinking about schema
evolution and schema migration more in
advance or is there really like some
other cost or benefit involved yes there
is an I think an important cost and
benefit in this case and I think that is
the question if you think about your
schema is that schema which is shared by
the multiple
applications or is it belongs to
elective a single application right and
letting you maybe example so imagine you
have their mobile game right and you
have a characters first characters have
probably no to properties right maybe
have you know some items in their
backpack and so on and so forth right
but what is the interesting thing about
this data it's only interpreted and
processed by a single application in
this case the dog store is absolutely
fantastic because I can use any kind of
complexity for my for example character
over ever object right and then it can
very conveniently store and retry that
from a database now let's say compare
that to your e-commerce application then
I may have let's say some sort of form
you know orders database right like a
kind of classical relationship example
which from which may be used by a lot of
different applications right one
application forward for forward facing
the users in their buying this stuff and
it is application which manages delivery
of those things and there is a third one
which use the same database which shows
the managers which goods are being sold
well and which are not
right in this case the relational
database is often much more more
convenient right because that saves us
from having to manage the schema
evolution in all three different
different applications is it because the
schema evolution is something that
structural in the database versus
something that's just logical in the
application layer that's right yes
because in this case if I just simply
have that game and I change one piece of
code which says hey now I added a couple
of more more things here couple of more
properties and that's it right it stores
a new object sits in a new format it's
processed objects and they're all the
new format that's easy if I have five
applications right and then I have to
teach every single those five
applications now to deal with objects of
a different
kinds of a different structure right
which is complicated but even more so it
is error-prone right
remember database is something which is
often very critical for your for your
business all right in this case and some
mistakes right may cost you many
thousands or even you know millions and
more or more dollars right in this case
so the you often vary for certain
applications you've very very much about
database working correctly or actually
application working correctly of
database how do I evaluate when a
database is mature enough to be used in
a critical system again I would repeat
the same thing I said before right there
is a safety in numbers at large extent
right I mean if you know a lot of people
have used that database already right in
a similar circumstances that increases
the probability right what you will be
successful as well or if you run to
travels you would be able to resolve
them right but at the same time of
course if that's the case right then no
new databases would come to a picture
right in this case and and and that
shows us another path in many cases
where early adopters so they start to
deploy those new databases sometimes
they are smart right and they deploy
them in less business critical
environments where mistakes are okay
right and you know downtime doesn't cost
a lot of money or people lives right and
then those database can get polished
sometimes you know that's not the case
right and we can see somebody doing
gauging the reckless decisions getting
the databases in in the environment
which is not it's not ready for right in
this case I mean my approach would be to
be practical here but also do not rely
just on other people experience often
what I found it would be surprising
discovery what certain things which
worked for other people do
not work for you because you're doing
certain things differently and you know
somehow nobody did it exactly the same
way right which can cause bugs or
performance problems and and so on and
so forth right so the best tool in my
opinion is at least doing some sort of a
proof of concept if a database
acknowledges you think maybe good good
fit right and to get a feel how it's it
actually does what is important for you
for some people things like scalability
is important then you want to test that
or or efficiency tested as well in some
cases it may be for example language
support right if you specifically look
at where relational databases SQL is so
powerful so worried about and no to SQL
no to relational databases support SQL
language in exactly the same way right
so you may want to test what it has
there SQL language features you would
like you would like to use right now I
think what is also it becomes
increasingly important is non-technical
properties right especially in the
enterprise space which is asking
questions about well what about the
vendor viability right because hey if
you know some of the open source
database companies like you know rethink
DB or basha which was signal company
behind technology called ruairioc you
know went on the right and you don't
want to to be stuck in situation where
your technology has you know no more
commercial support right so think about
that or some other I would say
operational aspects do we have dating at
rest encryption right origin
functionality which may be required it
by the compliance departments in the
enterprises for that technology to be
able to be used this gets into another
area that you've talked about and could
be important in the decision and that's
the licensing so we've already said that
there
reasons to prefer open-source databases
but there's some also some nuances
around the particular type of
open-source license can you talk about
that sure I think we look at the very
interesting time when it comes to
licenses in the open-source space right
I mean if you look at the traditional
open-source licenses they could be put
in relatively two buckets which are most
commonly used right it will be called
permissive licenses and copyleft
licenses right permissive license pretty
much it means you can take a software
and you know customize it and you know
maybe you know release the commercial
version of that if you if you like and
that's their license beyond behind the
technology such as such as Postgres
right or are you know apache license how
a lot of technology such as you know
hadoop would be licensed right the other
set of technologists we serve a type of
the other type of license is the
copyleft that pretty much means if you
are taken using this software then you
have to also stick to the soft you
release if it to be open source as well
right and the most notable examples in
this case that you have a MySQL which is
GPL license and MongoDB which until
recently used a GPL license right which
are both so called the copyleft licenses
right and why would vendor choose one or
another license if you think about your
permissive license then that really is
the best for adoption because then that
means a lot of users but also Java
commercial vendors can take your
technology and do whatever you want with
it and hence driving at upfront right
but that helped that will have a
downside or for having more
fragmentation potentially and also from
the vendor behind
technology to be able to to monetize it
right which is very important of course
with a lot of adventure founded modern
open source companies right the
companies behind the open-source
technology now here is a challenge these
things such as simply having a copyleft
license worked well and the times when a
software was distributed right on
compact discs right whatever now in an
age of a cloud that is not not good
enough right for example MySQL has GPL
license but at the same time the company
which probably makes the most money on
my school right now it's not Oracle who
owns my squirrel it's it's Amazon who
has a very popular Amazon and their
services and they're able to do that
even though they're my school is GPL
license because they are not really
distributing soft right they're just
running modified version of that
software themselves so they can do that
according to the GPL GPL license right
and that means I said that's the next
interest in evolution right there
number of of venture funded companies
open source company you can say hey you
know what we do not want cloud vendors
such as Amazon competing with us we want
to do something about that right and
that do something is typically not in
line with the spirit of the open-source
license but that is in line of them
defending their own commercial interests
right so what happened in this case is
the company radius they are are at
what's called the Commons clause which
would be better described is I want to
make all the money close to the apache
license right distributing some of the
radius models MongoDB very licensed
MongoDB in the in the SPL license you
also see confluent they change the
license for certain parts of the perfect
Africa platform right so I think there
is a very
that is a very interested trend how the
open source evolving from you know just
open source but very bad is permissive
license or copy left to wherever is to
kind of more shades of gray right if you
will there are some software which will
be truly open source and other will
behave we give you access to the source
code but there are a lot some
restrictions about how you can use or
modify that that software and obviously
from your standpoint right if you want
to avoid vendor lock-in you want maximum
freedom right you want maximum freedom
to be able to to support and change it
softer yourself if you like you want to
hire different vendors right in this
case if you don't want to hire it
in-house and not to be bound just by to
a single technology vendor for for
support and and other services right and
in this case that's why I would
encourage everybody to understand if you
are really dealing with open source or
with something which is called the open
source but it's not really in the spirit
of an open source software
what's a situation you've seen or that
you predict would be a problem caused by
these changes to the licensing so like
I'm thinking about the specific impacts
or problems that you've seen well it's
interesting right a lot of a switch
happened very recently
right so when I mentioned radius
confluence MongoDB although so it
happened in it last six months in in the
year of 2018 right and if you look at
the open source of adoption trends and
that's where most of the impact is
likely to be it often takes months and
years to really really much realize what
you can say think about the SSP L right
MongoDB is new license we can see is
what number of entities such as Fedora
projects Debian they already judge what
they do not consider that as an open
source license
due to those reasons there MongoDB is
being removed from Debian right from
fedora and from next version of Red Hat
Red Hat Enterprise Linux right is that
going to be immediately causing some
loss of a user mind share or adoption
you know probably not over time affair
here's its it maybe now what that also
made is while it's may prevent it Amazon
right which is obviously a big you know
cloud boogeyman for many open-source
vendors it prevented them from releasing
MongoDB as a service but guess what they
did very least their MongoDB compatible
database right as a service still and
now we are just getting the
fragmentation that happen in in MongoDB
space and of course right now this
technology is rather simple it doesn't
have all features for MongoDB but Amazon
has a lot of resources and they show
that they can really do a great
engineering effort and you know in the
in a few years that may be very mature
technology and food in both mindshare
from one goodie be as well as a as a
business so that's what we see now but
hey you know I said if you don't I don't
know how it's going to play out we're
almost out of time so I wanted to give
you opportunity to talk about anything
else any other important topics that we
didn't cover yeah I want to go back to
the topic we discussed at the start of
his conversation right and I think that
was a very interesting topic right about
how does cloud impact open source right
and what you can see of course in this
case there is this there is important
impact right there we see a number of
users which would traditionally use open
source software they're not quite using
open source we're using open source
compatible cloud versions because of
convenience and that's what
they care about first and foremost right
and I think this is from one extent is a
worrying trend but from other extent
extent I think that is something we will
see some changes in the coming years
right like well if you remember right or
maybe read about the mid 90s right then
internet was was born actually often
sort of would still out there but tools
like open source rating system Linux
MySQL and so on so Vera we're not really
good enough right in this case son
Oracle they're much better we're much
more mature right and that's what people
use but then open source technologies
they caught up right over time it's just
what they take time to happen and I see
what a lot of the similar things
happening in the in the cloud now as
well right we are see in there a lot of
companies coming together especially
behind the kubernetes effort right which
really allows us to write their
applications for the cloud conveniently
right not just for a single single node
and that really allows to create the new
generation of applications which are
easy to use same as Amazon or ES right
or MongoDB Atlas but which are
completely open source right and they
just see the first sign there's the
first generation of applications coming
up they're not as mature but I would
expect it within you know next three to
five years we'll have the new generation
of those cloud native open source
applications which can give quite a bit
of competition to those cloud the cloud
vendors platforms right which require
login so what's the takeaway for someone
who's creating a new application are you
are you saying that it's they should
just use the cloud provided solution for
now and keep their eye on these new
technologies or is it really critical
for them to avoid lock-in well I think
the question in this case is
as if it depends right because if you
are right in the relatively small
application in this case that is using
the cloud is a very practical way for
you to do you know use what works best
now right right be practical now if you
are the enterprise right which has a you
know 10 years flying horizon and which
really wants to compete with technology
so all for a long term I know many of
those technology companies are now
invested investing massively in a
carbonaceous effort and try to move as
many technologies to that technology as
possible because you know what they
already have seen their Amazon Cloud
bills and we know those are not pretty
right or other cloud providers right and
they want to make sure we maintain and
enhance their negotiating power and
ability to move our clothes between the
clouds great glad we covered that Peter
how can listeners find out more about
what you're doing
follow you and find out more about
Percona oh well yes you can find us at
devil you can calm of course
right we have a blog which has a lot of
wonderful technical information you can
also follow me personally on Twitter
which you probably just see including
the links for podcast yeah that's right
I'll include a link to your Twitter and
blog in the show notes okay thank you
thanks for being on the show Peter for
software engineering radio this has been
Nate black thanks for listening thanks
for listening the se radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us a team at SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening